Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. Dan Seymour Papers, 1951-1974 RL.00747
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Dan Seymour papers
1951-1974
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company
RL.00747
21.5 Linear Feet
16,125 Items
Consists of correspondence, office files, memoranda, notes, client files and some advertisements, reports, charts, reprints, schedules, scripts, printed material, and calendars. The collection documents advertising history, especially television and the management of client accounts; the development of television shows and other aspects of television programming, including the selection of actors and audience profiles; advertising clients' account histories; the corporate administration of the J. Walter Thompson Company; and the career of Dan Seymour. There is limited material about Seymour prior to his employment by the J. Walter Thompson Company in 1955 or after his retirement from it in 1974. Clients of the company represented in the collection include Eastman Kodak Company, Ford Motor Company, Kraft Foods Company, Lever Brothers Company, and Liggett & Myers Tobacco Company. There is considerable overlap in the content of the series in this collection.
Access Restrictions
Access to some portions of the Dan Seymour Papers is restricted.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Dan Seymour Papers were transferred to the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library from the J. Walter Thompson Company in 1987. Processing of this collection was supported in part by gifts from the J. Walter Thompson Company Fund and the John and Kelly Hartman Foundation.
Biographical Note
Chronology
1914, June 28 Born, New York, N. Y.
1935 Received A.B. from Amherst College; Married Louise Scharff
1935-1956 Announcer, WNAC (Yankee Network), Boston
1936-1940 Announcer, Columbia Broadcasting System, New York
1940-1949 Freelance announcer and producer
1949-1955 Radio-Television Programming and Production, Young and Rubicam agency, New York
1953 Vice-President, Young and Rubicam agency, New York
1955, Oct. Director, Radio-Television Department, New York Office, J. Walter Thompson Company
1955, Dec. Elected Vice-President, J. Walter Thompson Company
1958, June Elected to the Board of Directors, J. Walter Thompson Company
1960, Sept. Elected to the Executive Committee, J. Walter Thompson Company
1960, Nov. Operations Committee, J. Walter Thompson Company
1961, Feb. Elected Senior Vice-President, J. Walter Thompson Company
1963, Feb. Elected Chairman of the Executive Committee and Chief Administrative Officer, J. Walter Thompson Company
1964, June Elected President and Chief Operating Officer, J. Walter Thompson Company
1967 Elected Chief Executive Officer, J. Walter Thompson Company
1972, June-1974 Chairman of the Board, J. Walter Thompson Company
1974, June Retired from J. Walter Thompson Company
1982, July 27 Died, New York, N. Y.
Dan Seymour was a member of the following advertising, marketing, and broadcasting organizations: the American Association of Advertising Agencies; the Marketing Science Institute (1960s); and the Academy of Television Arts and Sciences. Civic activities in which Dan Seymour participated include the Executive Committee of the Boy's Clubs of America, the Veterans Hospital Radio and Television (Bedside Network), and the Ad Hoc Advisory Group on the Presidential Vote for Puerto Rico (1971). For further biographical information, see the Biographical Information Series of the J. Walter Thompson Company Archives.
Collection Overview
The papers of Dan Seymour span the years 1951 to 1974, although the bulk of the material dates from 1955 to the 1960s. They consist of correspondence, office files, memoranda, notes, client files and some advertisements, reports, charts, reprints, schedules, scripts, printed material, and calendars. The collection documents advertising history, especially television and the management of client accounts; the development of television shows and other aspects of television programming, including the selection of actors and audience profiles; advertising clients' account histories; the corporate administration of the J. Walter Thompson Company; and the career of Seymour. There is limited material about Seymour prior to his employment by the J. Walter Thompson Company in 1955 or after his retirement from it in 1974. Clients of the company represented in the collection include the Eastman Kodak Company, the Ford Motor Company, the Kraft Foods Company, the Lever Brothers Company, and the Liggett and Myers Tobacco Company. There is considerable overlap in the content of the series in this collection.
The work of the J. Walter Thompson Company Radio-Television Department, primarily in television, is chiefly documented in the Radio-Television Series. When he joined the company, Seymour's first objective was to reorganize its radio and television operations into a single Radio-Television Department because television had emerged as the leading media in the United States in the 1950s. The process of reorganization and overall administration of the Radio-Television Department is documented throughout the Radio-Television Department Series (Office Files and Thompson Company Offices). Aspects of administration documented include: the roles of company unit heads, such as the group heads or domestic office heads; relationships among the various units; operations of review boards; new business development; client relationships; and budgets. The New York office and other domestic offices, especially the Hollywood, Chicago, and Detroit offices, were key corporate links in television-related advertising. The New York office's radio and television activities are documented throughout Radio-Television Department Series; the Thompson Company Offices Subseries primarily documents the radio and television work of other domestic offices, but it includes a small amount of information about the New York office's operations. There is additional documentation for the Radio-Television Department in the Corporate Administration Series (Office Files).
Specific television programs and the scheduling of client advertising are documented in the Radio-Television Department Series (Programming), but radio programming is minimally represented. Availabilities and the Show Files are bound compilations of documents which provide information about programs available for J. Walter Thompson Company clients to sponsor. There are synopses of shows, which usually include descriptions of actors, directors, and producers, and scripts of various lengths. The Talent Showcase files appear to serve a similar function to those of the Availabilities and Show Files. More information on program availabilities for specific networks is in the Radio-Television Department Series (Networks). Screening reports, which are synopses of programs viewed by company staff, are scattered throughout the Availabilities and the Show Files binders, but the majority of the screening reports are found in the Radio-Television Department Series (Thompson Company Offices), especially for the Chicago, Hollywood, and New York offices. Some files for specific programs that were sponsored by company clients are in the Clients Series.
There is much overlap between the Corporate Administration Series and the Radio-Television Department Series in that both series contain information on the J. Walter Thompson Company's role in television advertising. The Radio-Television Department Series contains material on this topic from 1955, when Seymour was the director of this department, to 1967, during which time Seymour was also involved in company-wide management. The Corporate Administration Series also includes material related to the Radio-Television Department.
Not only does the collection document television advertising, it also pertains to Seymour's account management of J. Walter Thompson Company clients. In fact the Clients Series, which documents this activity, comprises almost one-half of the collection. This series particularly concerns advertising strategies, billings, the development of new business, and negotiations with clients. It also documents the conceptualization and production of television shows and motion pictures that were sponsored by individual clients. The call reports are records of telephone or personal contacts with clients and include information on many aspects of JWT-client relationships. Programs sponsored by the Eastman Kodak, Ford Motor, Kraft Food, Lever Brothers, and Liggett and Myers Tobacco companies are especially well described. Documentation for client accounts is also in the Review Board files of the Corporate Administration Series (Office Files) and scattered throughout the Radio-Television Department Series (Programming).
In addition to client activity, the collection reflects the corporate business of the company, especially as conducted through the New York office, in the Corporate Administration Series (Correspondence). In particular the Reading Files and the Norman H. Strouse correspondence pertain to this corporate activity. The series also includes general correspondence and topical files that are peripherally related to company operations. Strouse's letters concern corporate administration and management at the level of the President, and reflect the information exchanges and cooperation among the company's executive officers. The Strouse files span the period in which Seymour was elected to the Executive Committee and continue through his election to the Presidency of the company, succeeding Strouse. As Chairman of the Executive Committee, Seymour was responsible for all of the company's domestic operations. The Executive Committee files in the Corporate Administration Series (Office Files), include monthly reports for "New Projects" and include client names, the product or services involved, the nature of the project, and costs.
The Corporate Administration Series (Thompson Company Offices) also documents organizational issues in domestic offices other than the New York office. The establishment of the Chicago Office's review boards is documented in the subseries. The reports in the Corporate Administration Series (Reports), reflect research and concerns about internal J. Walter Thompson Company operations as well as client and public relations issues.
In the late 1930s through 1950, before Seymour joined the J. Walter Thompson Company, he developed relationships with radio and television celebrities, client-sponsors of programs, network and studio personnel, and advertising executives. These relationships continued in Seymour's work as an advertising executive in Young and Rubicam and the J. Walter Thompson Company. The congratulatory correspondence, mostly responses to Seymour's promotions, in the Radio-Television Series, the Corporate Administration Series, and the Miscellaneous Series documents these relationships. The invitations to professional and social events in the Corporate Administration Series (Correspondence) reflect the business of the corporate world beyond the J. Walter Thompson Company.
Television advertising -- United States -- History; Broadcast advertising; Advertising agencies -- New York; Television broadcasting -- United States -- History; Advertising -- Management; Advertising executives; Advertising campaigns; Corporate culture -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Ford Motor Company; Eastman Kodak Company; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; Lever Brothers Company; Liggett & Myers Tobacco Company; Kraft Foods Company; J. Walter Thompson Company
- Radio-Television Department Series, 1953-1967, undated bulk 1954-1963.
  Scope and Contents note
  Divided into six subseries: Correspondence, Office Files, J. Walter Thompson Company Offices, Programming, Networks, and Reports.
  - Correspondence Subseries
    Radio-Television Department: Correspondence Subseries, 1955-1962.Includes correspondence, printed material, and clippings.
    - 1955-1962 (Box 1)
    - Congratulatory, 1955, Aug.-Oct. (Box 1)
  - Office Files Subseries
    Radio-Television Department: Office Files Subseries, 1953-1963(bulk 1955-1960). Includes correspondence, memoranda, notes, reports, presentation exhibits, printed material, and clippings. See also oversize materials. Arranged into a chronological section, followed by subject files, with clippings at the end; arranged chronologically therein.
    - 1953-1962, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - Credentials, including drafts and notes, 1953-1956 (Box 1)
    - Evening homes using TV study, 1957-1960 (Box 2)
    - "General TV Presentation": New Business, ca. 1955Local Live TV Group," 1953-1956? (Box 2)
    - MCA TV/ American Football League, 1962 (Box 2)
    - New business, 1956 (Box 2)
    - Presentation (with N. Strouse?) on JWT's capabilities with television, 1955 (Box 2)
    - Radio-Television Exploitation Services, 1957 (Box 2)
    - Talent, 1956 (Box 2)
    - Television Advisory Group, 1963 (Box 2)
    - (JWT) Television Workshop (channel 3); JWT Color Television Workshop, 1955-1963 (Box 2)
    - TV Art Group, 1956 (Box 2)
    - Clippings:
      - 1955-1962 (Box 2)
      - Canadian, 1956 (Box 2)
  - J. Walter Thompson Company Offices Subseries
    Radio-Television Department: J. Walter Thompson Company Offices Subseries, 1955-1962.Includes correspondence, memoranda, and reports. Arranged alphabetically by the name of the office, or by subject, then chronologically therein.
    - Chicago: (Box 2)
      - Public Relations Department, 1956 (Box 2)
      - TV Availability reports, 1956, Sept.-Dec. (Box 2)
    - Hollywood, 1955-1961, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Hollywood, 1963 (Box 3)
    - Hollywood: Memoranda/Reports on TV-related subjects, including screenings, from Len White, 1955, Oct.-1962, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - New York: Screening reports, 1955-1956 (Box 3)
    - San Francisco: 1956-1961, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Sydney, 1962 (Box 3)
    - Tokyo, 1960-1961 (Box 3)
  - Programming Subseries
    Radio-Television Department: Programming Subseries, 1955-1967, undated(bulk 1955-1957). Includes memoranda, call reports, scripts, schedules, program proposals, reports and charts, and correspondence. The majority of the folder titles are adapted from original titles assigned by Seymour or from the titles of the enclosed documents. See also oversize materials. Arranged alphabetically by folder title, then chronologically therein.
    - Agents, scripts, studios, and stations, 1955, Nov.-1967, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Availabilities: (Box 4)
      - Lucian Chimene, 1956 (Box 4)
      - 1957, May-June, undated, 4 folders (Box 4)
    - Availabilities, 1958, Jan.-Oct., 5 folders (Box 5)
    - Availabilities, 1958, Aug.-Dec., undated, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Easter Show Proposal, Radio City Music Hall, 1956-1957 (Box 6)
    - "Landmark":
      - Personnel and presentation, 1955-1956 (Box 6)
      - Report and sample stories [Screen Gems/Columbia], 1956, undated (Box 6)
      - Script, 1956, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Mark Hellinger Theatre, 1950s (Box 6)
    - "Meet the Press," 1955-1956 (Box 7)
    - New programs:
      - 1954-1957, undated, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Broadcasting Department: Reports and correspondence, 1963-1964 (Box 7)
    - "Omnibus" ( CBS and NBC), 1955-1956
      - (Clients: Aluminium Limited, Douglas Aircraft, Institute of Life Insurance, Johns-Manville, Owens-Illinois Glass, and Scott Paper Co.) (Box 7)
    - Options for clients and shows, 1956 (Box 7)
    - Ratings:
      - Arbitron, 1961 (Box 7)
      - Share Trends, 1957-1964, undated (Box 7)
    - Records of network radio and TV programs with client sponsors for 1954-1957 seasons, 1957 (Box 7)
    - Rerun analysis, 1955, Dec. 4 (Box 7)
    - Research project: story values and ratings by Frank Wisbar, Barbara Television, 1956 (Box 7)
    - Screen Gems, 1956-1957 (Box 7)
    - Show Files, 1957, Feb. 1-5, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Show Files, 1957, Feb. 5-April, 4 folders (Box 8)
    - Talent Showcase, 1956, Jan.-Mar. (Box 8)
    - Talent Showcase, 1956, Apr.-Nov., 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Television Program Evaluations, 1960 (Box 9)
    - A Totally Different Comedy Concept, presentation by Radio-Television Department, 1960-1961 (Box 9)
  - Networks Subseries, 1953-1964
    Includes correspondence, memoranda, printed material, reprints, and schedules. Arranged alphabetically by the name of the network, then chronologically therein.
    - American Broadcasting Company, 1956-1962 (Box 9)
    - Columbia Broadcasting System:
      - 1956-1963 (Box 9)
      - Television as an Extension School of Democracy, by J. L. Van Volkenburg, President of CBS, 1953, Dec. 17 (Box 9)
    - National Broadcasting Company:
      - 1955-1964, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - "One Man's Family," 1954, Feb. (Box 9)
  - Radio-Television Department: Reports Subseries, 1956-1963.
    Includes reports and memoranda by the J. Walter Thompson Company. Arranged alphabetically by title.
    - "An Evaluation of Adult Daytime Television," 1961 (Box 10)
    - FCC Hearings: "In the Matter of the Study of Radio and Television Broadcasting," 1961, Sept. 26-Oct. 6 (Box 10)
    - "J. Walter Thompson Overseas Films," 1956, Aug. (Box 10)
    - "A New Method of Classifying Television Programs," 1961, Apr. (Box 10)
    - "Performer Popularity Analysis," 1961, May-Aug. (Box 10)
    - "Pretesting TV Commercials," Research Department, 1957 (Box 10)
    - "Recent Pioneering Research," 1960-1961 (Box 10)
    - "Review of Major Radio and Television Program Rating Services," 1957 (Box 10)
    - "Significant New Developments in Media," 1961 (Box 10)
    - " Sindlinger and Nielsen Media Data Comparison," 1963 (Box 10)
    - "Television Program Image Study," 1960-1961 (Box 10)
    - "TV Commercial Pretesting for Advertising Strategy," 1961 (Box 10)
    - "TV-Q Trend Reports," 1962 (Box 10)
- Corporate Administration Series, 1955-1973, undated (bulk 1956-1965).
  Divided into five subseries: Correspondence, Office Files, J. Walter Thompson Company Offices, Reports, and Miscellaneous.
  - Corporate Administration: Correspondence Subseries, 1958-1974 (bulk 1960-1970).
    Includes correspondence, memoranda, and attachments such as printed materials, speeches, clippings, and notes. See also oversize material. Arranged with general correspondence first, followed by congratulatory letters, invitations, Norman H. Strouse correspondence, and Reading Files. Arranged chronologically within folders, except for the Reading Files.
    The contents of the Reading Files, which consist of incoming and outgoing correspondence, are arranged numerically by numbers assigned by Seymour, however, the order roughly correlates with chronological order. For each year, there is an alphabetical index of correspondents and all names are listed with the corresponding number(s) of their letter(s) in the Reading Files.
    - 1961, Jan.-1964, Nov. (Box 11)
    - Congratulatory, 1958-1964, 8 folders (Box 11)
    - Congratulatory, 1964-1967, 7 folders (Box 12)
    - Congratulatory, 1967 (Box 13)
    - Invitations, 1963-1964, 5 folders (Box 13)
    - Strouse, Norman H., 1960-1961, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Strouse, Norman H., 1962-1964, 4 folders (Box 14)
    - Reading File and index, 1970, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Reading File and index, 1970, July-1972, 6 folders (Box 15)
    - Reading File and index, 1973-1974, 4 folders (Box 16)
  - Corporate Administration: Office Files Subseries, 1955-1971 (bulk 1960s).
    Includes correspondence, memoranda, speeches, charts and tables, reports, and clippings. Arranged into general, chronological files; followed by subject files arranged by folder title and chronologically therein; with clippings at the end.
    - 1961-1963, 3 folders (Box 16)
    - 1964-1967, 4 folders (Box 17)
    - (JWT) Art Program and Art Decor for corporate offices, 1961-1965 (Box 17)
    - Billings to clients, 1962 (Box 17)
    - (JWT) Board of Directors meetings, 1961-1962 (Box 17)
    - Christmas file, 1963 (Box 17)
    - Creative Department: Reorganization, 1964 (Box 18a)
    - Diners Fugazy Travel and Incentive Co., 1970 (Box 18a)
    - Editorial Department: Reorganization, 1964 (Box 18a)
    - Executive Committee:
      - 1961-1962, 2 folders (Box 18a)
      - Distribution of Arno H. Johnson pamphlet, 1962 (Box 18a)
    - Forward Planning: Preparation of marketing strategy by Sidney Olson, 1960, Nov. 28 (Box 18a)
    - (JWT) House Advertising, 1963-1964 (Box 18a)
    - House Advertising Committee, 1961 (Box 18a)
    - International offices, 1961-1962 (Box 18a)
    - J. Walter Thompson Advertising (analysis and credential development), 1961 (Box 18a)
    - J. Walter Thompson presidency, text for Advertising Age, 1964 (Box 18a)
    - JWT World planning, 1963 (Box 18a)
    - Marketing Department, 1963 (Box 18a)
    - Media Department, 1957, 1963 (Box 18a)
    - MPO Videotronics collaboration with J. Walter Thompson, 1963-1964 (Box 18a)
    - New Business: (Box 18b)
      - 1955-1957, 2 folders (Box 18b)
      - (Clients: American Chicle Co., Anheuser-Busch, B.F. Goodrich Tire Co., Diamond Crystal Salt, General Foods, Lever Brothers Co., Schick, Shulton Foods, and Manhattan Shirt Co.) (Box 18b)
    - Dan Seymour notes, 1956-1957
      - (Clients: B.F. Goodrich Tire Co., Columbia Broadcasting System, and Ford Motor Company) (Box 18b)
    - Personnel: Restricted (Box 19)
      - 1955-1964, 2 folders (Box 19)
      - Candidates, 1970-1971 (Box 19)
      - Investigation by Smith, Dingwall Associates, 1963-1964 (Box 19)
      - Resumes and reports, 1961-1964, 4 folders (Box 19)
    - (JWT) Profit Sharing Plan and Trust, 1959-1962 (Box 20)
    - Research Department, 1963 (Box 20)
    - Review Board:
      - 1963-1964, 3 folders (Box 20)
      - (Clients: Aluminium Limited, American Electric Power Service, American Petroleum Institute, Associated Hospital Service of New York, Brillo Manufacturing Co., Chesebrough-Pond's, Chunky Corp. Rowntree, Congoleum-Nairn, Francis I. duPont and Co., Douglas Aircraft Co., Eastman Kodak Co., Good Humour Corp., Institute of Life Insurance, Intercontinental Hotels Corp., Irving Trust Co., Lever Brothers Co., Liebmann Breweries, Liggett and Myers Tobacco Co., Massachusetts Mutual Life Insurance Co., McGraw-Edison Dictating Equipment, Mentholatum Co., National Car Rental System, New Holland Machine Co., New York World's Fair, Panagra (Pan American-Grace Airways), Phillips Petroleum Co., Purolator Products, Radio Corporation of America General (RCA), Reader's Digest Services, R.T. French Co., Scott Paper Co., Singer Co., Standard Brands, United States Brewers Assoc., United States Lines, United States Playing Card Co., Warner-Lambert, and W.F. Young) (Box 20)
      - General plans, 1962-1963 (Box 20)
      - New procedures, 1964 (Box 20)
      - Procedures: Report with appendices, 1964 (Box 20)
      - (Clients: Pan American World Airways and Standard Brands) (Box 20)
      - Eastman Kodak, 1962 (Box 20)
      - Ford Division, 1964 (Box 20)
      - Johns-Manville, 1956 (Box 20)
      - Liggett and Myers Tobacco Co., 1962 (Box 20)
      - Scott Paper Co., 1964 (Box 20)
      - Standard Brands: Planters Nut and Chocolate Company, 1963 (Box 20)
    - Speeches:
      - By non-JWT staff, 1957-1962 (Box 20)
      - Johnson, Arno H., "Summary of Current Economic Situation," 1962, June 26 (Box 20)
      - Jones, Richard P., "A Look at the Future of Radio," 1962, Dec. 4 (Box 20)